Preliminary Inventory to the Clarence Clemens Clendenen Papers, 1881-1968
Hoover Institution Archives
Clarence Clemens Clendenen Papers
1881-1968
68022
Hoover Institution Archives
21 manuscript boxes, 4 card file boxes, 7 envelopes, 9 phonotapes 11 linear feet
Printed matter, biographical notes, interviews, diaries, correspondence, army manuals, research notes, photographs, and maps, relating to American military history, especially during World War II and the Vietnamese War, and to the Punitive Expedition in Mexico in 1916.
Clendenen, Clarence Clemens
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
United States. Army--History--Punitive Expedition into Mexico, 1916; Mexico--History--Revolution, 1910-1920.; Mexico.; Phonotapes.; United States--Armed Forces.; United States--History, Military.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Recruiting material (Box 1)
- Military miscellany (Folder b.)
- Newspaper clippings of military interest (Box 2)
- National Guard material (Folder b.)
- Maps of Mexico (3) (Folder c.)
- Guide books (Box 3)
- Foreign phrase books (Folder b.)
- Army handbooks (Box 4)
- Army and Navy regulation manuals (Folder b.)
- Staff officers manual (Box 5)
- Army general orders, circulars and bulletins, (published), 1881-1916 (Folder b.)
- Communications handbook, 1944 (Folder c.)
- 6th Cavalry notes (Folder d.)
- Articles pertaining to Pancho Villa (Folder e.)
- Research notes (index cards) on book, United States and Pancho Villa (Box 6)
- Published articles on World War II (miscellaneous uncatalogued) (Box 7)
- Published materials on American military history: (Box 8)
  - Alison, John R., "The Most Unforgettable Character I've Ever Met: Col. Philip Cochran," in Readers' Digest, pp. 130-138, Oct. 1958
  - Apter, Howard, "Eight Golden Arrows of the E.T.O.," in Saga, pp. 49-53, Summer, 1964
  - Apter, Howard, "Old Ironsides, Saga of the 1st Armored Division," in Saga, 12 p., Dec. 1962
  - Atwater, James, "Last Stand of the Big Bomber," in Saturday Evening Post, pp. 13-16, June 20, 1964
  - Baren, Harry G., "My Combat Mission with Lyndon Johnson," in Saga, 8 p., July 1964
  - Belot, Raymond de, "The French Fleet in Being," in U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 1056-1067, Oct. 1951
  - Boatner, Haydon L., "How I Crushed the Reds on Koje Island," in Saga, pp. 17-21, Summer 1964
  - Bowen, Charles F., Lost Virgin, Boston, Bruce Humphries, 7 p. End paper maps. Autographed copy, 1959, 32
  - Bueschel, Richard M., "World War II Japanese Aircraft A to Z," in Air Progress, pp. 35-38, June/July 1964.
  - Chavez, Patrick, "The American-led Sea Roughnecks Who Sank the Gronau, Jewel of Hitler's Mid-East Fleet," 7 p.
  - Clendenen, Clarence C., "A Few Notes and Personal Reminiscences Concerning Maj. Gen. Terry de la Mesa Allen," 2 1. Typed. Appended: "Cavalryman vs. Cowboy," True West, S-0, 1965
  - "The Cruise of the Great White Fleet" (1907), U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 86-97, Oct. 1958.
  - "D-Day Plus 20 Years," in S.F. Examiner, 16 p., June 7, 1964
  - Deyo, Morton L., "Sea Power: Its Meaning to the United States of America," address, Newcomen Society, Boston, 25 p., March 25, 1948
  - Eller, E. M., "Soviet Bid for the Sea," in U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 619-635, June 1955
  - Enthoven, Alan C., "Choosing Strategies and Selecting Weapon Systems," in U. S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 151-158., Jan. 1964
  - Ettman, Seymour, "Saga of the Hornet," in Prize Sea Stories Magazine, pp. 52-59, Spring 1964
  - "The Face of the Enemy," in Male, 4 p., Sept. 1964
  - Fletcher, James, "The Sea Battle That Couldn't Be Won," in Saga, 9 p., Dec. 1962
  - Fuchida, Mitsuo, "Five Fateful Minutes at Midway," in U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 660-665, June 1955
  - Gallagher, Richard, "GI Tiger-Bandit of Saipan," in Male, pp. 94-101., Feb. 1964
  - Gant, Matthew, "MacArthur's Finest Hours," in Impact, pp. 51-64, Aug. 1964 (Box 9)
  - Ginsburgh, Robert N., "The New Soviet Military Strategy," in U. S. Naval Institute Proceedings, 4 p., Jan. 1964
  - Gonzalez, Arturo S., Jr., "Report from South Viet Nam," in Elks Magazine, 6 p., Aug. 1964
  - Gottesfeld, Sam, "New Light on the MacArthur Snafus," in Real Combat Stories, 6 p., June 1964
  - Green, Montgomery M., "The Secret of Kremlin Warfare," in U. S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 1131-1141, Oct. 1954
  - Guttridge, Len, "'Hold Hill 314 Till Dead'," in Stag, 8 p., March 1964
  - Hay, George T., "Soldiers of the Queen," in The Scots Magazine, 7 p., Nov. 1957
  - Hearle, Douglas, "The Man Who Lived in Hell," in Impact, pp. 26-30, 71-74, Aug. 1964
  - Herndon, Booton, "From Custer to Korea: The 7th Cavalry," in Saga, pp. 70-79, Summer 1964
  - "Das Herz der 6. Armee," in Revue, 9 p., May 27, 1964.
  - Hewitt, H. Kent, "The Landing on Morocco, November 1942," in U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 1243-1253, Nov. 1952
  - Infield, Glenn, "The B-17 That Stalked Hitler's Buzz Bombs," in Saga, 7 p., March 1964
  - Irwin, Theodore, "The War Hero Who Inspired J.F.K.," in Saga, pp. 2-8(Joseph F. Kennedy, Jr.), Summer 1964
  - Jacobs, Bruce, "Sergeant York," in Saga, pp. 36-41, Summer 1964
  - Johnson, Arthur M., "Theodore Roosevelt and the Navy," in U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 76-82, Oct. 1958
  - Johnson, James Ralph, "Incident on Iwo Jima," in Saga, 2 p., Summer 1964
  - Jordan, Douglas Stuart, "Fisher's Folly: The Fabulous Furious," in U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 667-677, June 1955
  - Kaylin, Walter, "Take and Hold a Small Island Called Guadalcanal," in Men, 9 p., July 1964
  - Kraft, Joseph, "Hot Weapon in the Cold War," in Saturday Evening Post, 6 p., April 28, 1962.
  - Lansford, W. Douglas, "Gung Ho: The Story of Carlson's Raiders," in Saga, pp. 9-15, Summer 1964
  - Leckie, Robert, "Sub Sunk, Sub Sunk... Sub Sunk," in Saga, pp. 45-48, 71-74, June 1964
  - Lee, Bruce, "Best Kept Secret of World War II," in Saga, 8 p., July 1964
  - Lowe, George E., "The Specter of a 'Man on Horseback'," in U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 26-35, Jan. 1964
  - Mars, David, "If There's a Dirty War, Get Me Yarborough," in Male, pp, 38-42, 75-82, Feb. 1964.
  - Marshall, S. L. A., "The Forgotten GI's Who Saved D-Day," in Saga, pp. 13-16, 76-80, June 1964
  - Marshall, S. L. A., "The Generals Who Are Out to Kill Ike," in Saga, 6 p., Jan. 1964
  - Marshall, S. L. A., "The Taking of Hill 180...," in Men, 8 p., June 1964
  - Marshall, S. L. A., "Why Do They Slander Our Military Men?" in Saturday Evening Post, 6 p., Sept. 5, 1964
  - Meyerson, Victor, "I Led the Jap-Slaughtering Huks of Mindanao," in Real Combat Stories, 6 p., June 1964
  - Mirror, Article pertaining to General Jonathan M. Wainwright's reception in New York City, Sept. 14, 1945.
  - Mizrahi, Joseph V., "The Day the Germans Used Poison Gas," Man's Magazine, 6 p., July 1964
  - Momoto, Harotoshi, "I Commanded Japan's Fanatical Human Torpedoes," in Stag, 3 p., Jan. 1964
  - Moore, W. Robert, "Gilbert Islands in the Wake of Battle," in National Geographic Magazine, pp. 129-162, Feb. 1945
  - Nagle, Ferderick W., "Weather and Command Decision," in U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, 5 p., Jan. 1964
  - News, Sunday showing U.S. Army insignia, etc., June 10, 1945
  - O'Brien, Brien, "Fleet that Sailed Through a Jungle," in Prize Sea Stories Magazine, pp. 66-71, Spring 1964
  - Pearl, Jack, "MacArthur vs. Patten: Who was the Greater General?" in Saga, pp. 42-48, Summer 1964
  - Pearl, Jack, "They Hanged the Mutineers," in Saga, 6 p., Summer 1964
  - Pearl, Jack, "St. Mihiel: The Nightmare Battle of World War I," in Saga, 6 p., April 1964
  - "Prepare to Occupy," in Fortune, 1 v., Feb. 1943
  - Rankin, Robert H., "A History of Selective Service," in U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 1073-1081, Oct. 1951
  - Reinsch, Paul S., "Japan's Lone Hand," in Asia, 8 p., Feb.-March 1920 (Box 10)
  - Reynolds, Edward, "When the Dorchester Was Torpedoed," in the S.F. Examiner, 1 v., Feb. 2, 1964
  - Roll, George A., "Sea 'Powers' Control Forces," in U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 1073-1083., October 1954
  - Roustam Bek, Boris L. T., "The Red War," from Asia, Vol. XX, no. 2, 11 p., Feb.-March 1920
  - Ruge, Friedrich, "German Naval Strategy Across Two Worlds Wars," in U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 153-166., Feb 1955
  - Ruhe, William J., "War in the Silent World," in Prize Sea Stories Magazine, pp. 42-47, Spring 1964
  - Schlesinger, Arthur M., Jr., "The Supreme Cavalier," in S.F. Examiner, 1 v., Sept. 7, 1964
  - Scott, Robert Lee, Jr., "My Kid Brother's Confederate Eye," in Saga, pp. 60-64, Summer 1964
  - Six Juin 1964. "Numero historique: Il y a juste vingt ans ils debarquent," Paris Match, No. 791
  - Smith, C. Alphonso, "Martinique in World War II," in U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, 6 p., Feb. 1955
  - Smith, Stan, "Abandon Ship," in Man's Magazine, p., Feb. 1964, 6
  - Sol, Martin, "Commander Fluckey's Great Raid on Japan's '30 Ship Harbor'," in Men, 8 p., July 1964
  - Sold, Martin, "Dogfighting Phantom of the Pacific Air War," in Men, 6 p., Sept. 1964
  - Stuart, Arthur J., "The Mechanized Landing Force and the Blitz Beachhead," in U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 1209-1217, Nov. 1952
  - Sufrin, Mark, "Capt. Sam Durant, Tough Texan...," in Men, 1 v., June 1964
  - Tanabe, Yahachi, "I Sank the U.S.S. Yorktown at the Battle of Midway," in Stag, 10 p., March 1964
  - Tanabe, Yahachi, "I Sank the York at Midway," in Real, 5 p., Aug. 1964
  - "Total War for the United States, Fortune, 1 v., August 1941
  - 20th Anniversary of D-Day. Newspaper clippings, 1 v.
  - Ubell, Earl, "The Death of the Nike-Zeus," in Saturday Evening Post, pp. 15-18, June 4, 1964
  - United States Congress. Senate, Debate over the confirmation of General Ben Lear, May 20, 1943, Congressional Record, pp. 4745-4756
  - United States Naval War College. Comments on action reports covering activities in the Solomon Islands, 15 1., Aug. 7, 8, 9, 1942
  - "U.S. Navy," in Fortune, pp. 55-65, March 1938
  - Van Deurs, George, "The Segi Man," in U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 56-62, Oct. 1958
  - White, Thomas D., "Strategy and the Defense Intellectuals," in Saturday Evening Post, 3 p., May 4, 1963
  - Wygant, Bernard B., "Admiral Sims as I Knew Him," in U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, pp. 1088-1091, Oct. 1951
- Diaries, personal recollections, 1879-1942 (Box 11)
- Articles on Western Americana and Mexican history (Folder b.)
- Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 12)
- Army 201 file (Folder b.)
- Colonel Jerome W. Howe file (Folder c.)
- Letters by soldiers of the Kansas National Guard, mobilized on the Mexican border, 1 v., 1916 (Folder d.)
- "The Punitive Expedition of " 1 vol., 1916 (Box 13)
- Miscellaneous medals
- Unsorted material (Box 14-21.)
- Card file (Box 22-25.)
- Phonotapes (Oversize Tape cabinet)
  - Clovis Ethelbert Byers undated speech about military chaplins (Tape-cabinet Tape cabinet)
    Access
    Use copy reference number: 68022_a_0008886
    Scope and Contents note
    Major General C. E. Byers recalls the history and importance of chaplains in the United States military. He speaks about experiences of the country from the revolution through World War II and the Korean conflict.
  - Colonel Clarence C. Clendenen interviews Major General William Ord Ryan (Tape-cabinet Tape cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 68022_a_0008881
    Interview with Major General William Ord Ryan, U. S. Air Force, Retired, concerning his experiences as a lieutenant in the 7th cavalry, in the Punitive Expedition of 1916, and further remarks on his military career.
    Interviewer is Col. Clarence C. Clendenen as stated in his letter to Fraur Lanner, Oct. 10, 1974.
  - Confession of Librado Saenz Pardo Martinez and interview with Colonel Merlin J. Chadey, 03 October 1957-31 May 1964 (Tape-cabinet Tape cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 68022_a_0008891
    Confession of Librado Saenz Pardo Martinez, assassin of Pancho Villa. Recorded 10/3/57 by William V. Morrison of El Paso, Texas
    Colonel Merlin J. Chadsey, retired cavalry - recorded at Fort Union, National Mon by Homer Hasting, June 64.
  - Interview with Major Walter Estes, 21 April 1964 (Tape-cabinet Tape cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 68022_a_0008882
    Interview with Major Walter Estes, retired Calvary Officer, recorded by the Fort Union National Monument, 1964
- Photographs, 468 photos and 61 negatives / 7 envelopes (Folder Photo file)
  - 118 photos concerning Clendenden's attendance to West Point and the Cavalry School, undated (Folder A)
    Includes portraits of his classmates, graduation ceremonies and his participation in many equestrian events.
  - 65 photos and 61 negatives of the Punitive, undated (Folder B1)
  - Expedition to Mexico, including photos of Villa, Obregon and U.S. Infantry, undated (Folder B2)
  - 26 photos of Colonel Clarence C. Clendenen's stay in Japan concerning the 1st Cavalry Division, the International War Crimes Commission and many tourist attractions, undated (Folder C)
  - Album containing 125 photos of Colonel Clarence C. Clendenen's stay in Japan relating to War Crimes Commission and travel photos, undated (Folder fD)
  - 15 photos of Colonel Clendenen in Michigan State College, South Dakota State College, St. John's University and the University of Iowa in which he was the head of the R.O.T.C. programs, undated (Folder E)
  - 13 photos of the Negrito barrios in the Philippines where he was stationed, 1926 (Folder F)
  - 96 miscellaneous personal and military photos, undated (Folder G)
  - 10 miscellaneous photos, undated (Folder mH)
  - 4 miscellaneous photos, undated (Folder dr.1)